# JULIETA ARANCIO

#### **SUMMARY**

I am a researcher in Science and Technology Studies, an advocate for democratization of science and technology and a mentor for open hardware projects.

You will usually find me in roles of translation between different kinds of expertise, in projects at the crossroads of technology, sustainability, science and education.

#### LANGUAGES

I speak Spanish (native), English (bilingual), French (A2) and some Portuguese.

CONTACT



julieta.aranc.io



jarancio@unsam.edu.ar



@cassandreces

### **EDUCATION**

#### PHD IN SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY STUDIES

Universidad Nacional de Quilmes (2021)

My thesis (outstanding 10 with recommendation for publication) is titled "Technologies from dialogues: Open science hardware and democratization in the 'peripheria'" and is available in Spanish at the UNQ online repository.

#### LIC. IN ENVIRONMENTAL SCIENCE

Universidad de Buenos Aires (2011)

5-year degree at Agronomy College, orientation technology. My thesis was titled "Quality assessment of sediments of the Reconquista River (Buenos Aires), with emphasis in heavy metals" and is available in Spanish at the FAUBA online repository.

#### **EXPERIENCE**

# ASSOCIATE RESEARCHER (2015-PRESENT)

CENIT - STEPS Hub Latin America

Doctoral researcher (2016-2021). Collaborator in 'Open, Collaborative and Alternative Science: overcoming health, inclusion and environmental challenges in Argentina' (2015-2016) funded by the International Development Research Centre, Canada (OCSDnet).

### LEAD AUTHOR (MARCH 2021-PRESENT)

Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars

Lead researcher and writer of a white paper seeking to understand the value of low cost and open source hardware for scientific research.

# WRITER (FEB 2021-PRESENT)

Global Open Science Hardware Movement

Coordinate the drafting of workshop reports and a policy brief targeting universities' technology transfer offices

# EDITOR (2020-PRESENT)

Journal of Open Hardware

Member of the Editorial Board of the Journal of Open Hardware (JOH), a peer reviewed open access publication for open hardware research and development.

#### **CONSULTANT (2020-PRESENT)**

Appropedia Foundation

Consultation services for a project in partnership with Intuitive Foundation (US), on the design and implementation of an ontology for remote learning of medical skills.

## MENTOR FOR SDG PROJECTS (JUL-SEP 2018)

Geneva-Tsinghua Initiative, University of Geneva

Mentor of Master's students' projects addressing the SDGs with a focus on challenge-based learning, community building and management of open source projects.

# **SKILLS**

SOFT SKILLS

Conducting interviews, facilitating sessions with multiple stakeholders, collecting and analyzing big volumes of qualitative data, writing and editing of scientific materials. RESEARCH

Public speaking, writing for technical, informed and general audiences, basic audio and video editing, radio production, COMMUNICATIONS educational game design for virtual sessions.

Project management, problem-solving, conflict

management, mentoring, fundraising, collaborative work, international events organization.

Version control tools (git/GitHub/GitLab), basic web development (HTML, CSS, JS), Python and R scripts for data analysis, linked data ontology design using Protegé, operation of digital fabrication tools and programming of educational boards like Arduino, ESP32 or microBIT. **TECHNICAL** 

# **ONGOING PROJECTS**

#### OPEN HARDWARE MAKERS

openhardware.space

Co-founder (2019) of a global mentorship program for open hardware projects. General strategy, project management, curriculum design and communications. I led a global consultation for improving our curriculum with the open hardware community.

#### REGOSH

regosh.libres.cc

Co-founder (2017) of the network, ex-coordinator of Buenos Aires node, in charge of the strategy working group. I co-organized a regional residency in 2019, having previously co-organized a Global Open Science Hardware (GOSH) event in Shenzhen, China, in 2018.

# **FUNDING RECEIVED**

#### ALFRED P. SLOAN FOUNDATION (2021-2023)

Postdoctoral funding (USD 220,000) for two years at Drexel University, under supervision of Asoc. Prof. Gwen Ottinger

# **MOZILLA FOUNDATION (2020)**

Personal grant (USD 12,000) to advance community building

#### SHUTTLEWORTH FOUNDATION (2020)

Personal grant (USD 5,000) to advance project LogAir

NATIONAL SCIENCE AND RESEARCH COUNCIL OF ARGENTINA (2016) Full 5-years scholarship for pursuing my PhD

### **ACADEMIC WRITING**

Arancio, J.; Arza, V.; Fressoli, M. (2020, August 18-21) Opening Tools For Opening Science: Lessons From Global Open Science Hardware Initiatives In Africa And Latin America, 4S/EASST Conference 2020 - Prague, Czech Republic (Virtual)

Arancio, J. C. (2020, July 17). Opening Up The Tools For Doing Science: The Case Of The Global Open Science Hardware Movement. SocArXiv https://doi.org/10.31235

Arancio, J. 'Open science hardware: towards more democratic science and technology in Latin America?' Proceedings of 15th International Symposium on Open Collaboration, University of Skövde, 2019.

Arancio, J.; Molloy, J. 'The Global Open Science Hardware Roadmap: A Collaborative Effort towards Democratising Science Hardware', extended abstract for Tech4Dev Conference 2018 - UNESCO/EPFL (Lausanne, SZ)

Arancio, J.; Sebastian, S.; Schwertz-Weirich, A.; Actis, G.; Cremaschi, A.; Arancibia, F.; Van Zwanenberg, P.; Fressoli, M. 'Relato de experiencia - Workshop internacional de desarrollo abierto y colaborativo' in Liinc Em Revista, 2018 https://doi.org/10.18617/liinc.v14i1.4132

# **NON-ACADEMIC WRITING**

Arancio, J. 'Open Science Hardware contributes to aligning the research agenda with societal needs', in Journal of Open Hardware Blog,  $2020\,$ 

Dosemagen, S; Arancio, J. 'Open Hardware Distribution & Documentation Working Group series', in Journal of Open Hardware Blog, 2020

Arancio, J. 'Open science hardware across the Andes' in GOSH blog, 2018

Arancio, J. 'GOSH Roadmap: democratising technology, from a Latin American perspective', in STEPS Centre Blog, 2018

Arancio, J. 'OpenCon 2017: Des-idealizando lo abierto para una mejor apertura' in PlanC blog, 2018

Arancio, J.; Fressoli, M.; Arza, V. 'Agroecology meets open source technologies' in OCSDnet Blog, 2016

#### **CONFERENCES & WORKSHOPS**

STS Switzerland 2021 Conference (15-17 February 2021, Virtual) - Presenting author 4S/EASST Conference (18-20 August 2020, Virtual) - Presenting author

Doctoral Consortium - OpenSym (2019, Sweden) - Presenting author

Global Open Science Hardware gathering (2018, China) - Organizing committee

Mozilla Festival (2018, London) - Presenting author

OpenCon Swiss (2018, Bern) - Speaker

Tech4Dev (2018, Lausanne) - Presenting author

TECNOx (2018, Chile) - Speaker